A Finding Aid to the Emilio Sanchez Papers, 1922-2012, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Emilio Sanchez papers
1922-2012
Archives of American Art
Sanchez, Emilio, 1921-1999
AAA.sancemil
Archival Resource Key
18.1 Linear feet
The collection measures 18.1 linear feet, dates from 1922 to 2012, and documents the career of Cuban born painter and printmaker, Emilio Sanchez. The collection includes letters to Sanchez, business records, photographs of the artist and sources for his artwork, many original sketches, printed material, and calendars.
Biographical Note
Emilio Sanchez was born in 1921 in Camaguey, Cuba. He left his native country in 1952 to settle in New York where he became a naturalized citizen of the United States. A prolific painter and printmaker, Sanchez received his formal education at the Art Students' League and Columbia University during the late 1930s, and had his first of many one-man shows in New York in 1949. Sanchez traveled throughout the world sketching his impressions of houses and other buildings and capturing the details of doorways, windows, light, and shadow in his paintings and prints. His paintings of residential architecture in Cuba and throughout the Caribbean are some of his best known works, but in the 1980s he turned much of his attention to the skyline of his adopted home, and was often drawn also to American cities and landscapes over the course of his career.
Sanchez's work is represented in major museums and private collections the world over, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, the Hirshhorn Museum, the National Museum in Havana, and the Cintas Collection. He completed numerous commissions in both the United States and Mexico, has illustrated several books, including Arte del Peru Colonial by Felipe Cossío del Pomar (published in 1958 by the Fondo de Cultura Económica in Mexico), and has exhibited extensively in solo and group exhibitions in locations such as Mexico City, Paris, Havana, Madrid, Puerto Rico, Chile, Colombia, and throughout the United States.
Sanchez died in July, 1999 at the age of 78.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Cuban born painter and print maker Emilio Sanchez comprise 18.1 linear feet of material dating from 1922 to 2012. The papers contain biographical information about Sanchez; letters from galleries and museums recording business transactions; letters from friends; photographs of his artwork and places he visited for inspiration; personal photographs; sketches; exhibition catalogs, announcements, and reviews; clippings; and calendars.
A major portion of the collection consists of sketchbooks and sketches that provide rich documentation of Sanchez's artistic development and his working methods, particularly from the 1950s to the 1970s. Many of the sketches have detailed notations about aspects of an image that Sanchez wanted to recall and capture in his work. Photographs also provide insight into the architecture and landscapes that provided sources of inspiration for Sanchez.
A 10.1 linear foot addition contains biographical materials, correspondence, writings, photographs, works of art, subject files, printed materials, and scrapbooks. Biographical materials include address books, birth certificates, naturalization documents, and family-related documents. Correspondence is personal and professional and is with family, friends and museums. Writings are personal and include a log book and a typed transcription (possibly incomplete). Photographs are of Sanchez, his family, works of art, and source subjects for works of art, as well as CD-Roms of works of art. Some photographs assembled by Hugh Harrison, long-time friend of the Sanchez. Works of art include 10 sketchbooks and loose sketches. Also included are a drawing and 4 prints by Estrella Fonts, Sanchez's mother. Subject files include a print register, appraisals, mailing lists, and consignments. Printed material includes exhibition announcements and clippings. Also included are 3 scrapbooks, 2000-2012, that chronicle the history of the Emilio Sanchez Foundation's activities, including press releases, photographs, and exhibition-related material and hard drives of the foundation's databases in Filemaker format.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as seven series. Records are generally arranged by subject category, and then chronologically.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1969-1977, undated (box 1; 4 folders)
Series 2: Letters and Business Records, 1956-1979 (box 1; 25 folders)
Series 3: Photographs, 1922-1979, undated (boxes 1-3; 51 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1950-1980, undated (boxes 3-4; 17 folders)
Series 5: Calendars, 1967-1976 (boxes 4-5; 7 folders)
Series 6: Sketches, circa 1940-1979, undated (boxes 5-6, sols 7-11, OV's 12-22, RD 23-24; 2.9 linear ft.)
Series 7: Unprocessed Addition to the Emilio Sanchez Papers, 1949-2012 (boxes 25-34, OV 35; 10.1 linear ft.)
Related Material
Papers of Emilio Sanchez can also be found at the Dade County Public Library in Florida.
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Emilio Sanchez in a series of gifts between 1975 and 1980, and in 2012 by Emilio Sanchez via Erik J. Stapper, Emilio Sanchez Foundation.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Photographs; Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Sketches; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Interviews; Sketchbooks; Latino and Latin American artists
- Biographical Material, 1957-2002, undated; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, 25; (box 1; 4 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains immunization records for travel, a passport, the transcript of an interview with Sanchez in which he discusses his work in detail, as well as several résumés and biographical information about the artist, such as lists of his work in public institutions and lists of his exhibitions.
  Addition material includes passports, immigration and naturalization records, address books, travel diaries, a biography, and material from Sanchez's memorial service.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
  Addition is arranged in chronological order.
  - Immunization Records, 1969-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview Transcript, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passport, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Résumés and Biographical Notes, 1967-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1956-1999; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 1, 25
  Correspondence consists of personal letters, correspondence with galleries, and correspondence with museums. Letters to Sanchez from 1965-1969 contains plats for the school house property in Wanamaker, Pennsylvania, that Sanchez purchased for studio space but ultimately sold because the area became too industrialized.
  The series is arranged chronologically. Letters with attachments are filed by the date of the most recent letter in the group, with attached material in reverse chronological order behind it.
  Addition material is grouped into personal correspondence, gallery correspondence, and museum correspondence. Material was pre-processed either by archive staff or the Emilio Sanchez trust, and items in the folder are maintained in the order it arrived.
  - Letters to Sanchez, 1956-1964, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-23)
- Photographs, 1922-1999, undated; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 8.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, 27-32; (boxes 1-3; 51 folders)
  This series contains primarily color snapshots, in addition to some black and white photgraphs, several negatives and slides, and a series of contact sheets. There are family and personal photographs; photographs taken on travels intended to be used as sources for artwork; and photographs of works of art by Sanchez. Family and personal photographs include two photographs of Sanchez with his family, including his father; photographs of Sanchez at the Fortuny Exposition in Madrid in 1964 and at a 1966 exhibition in New York City; snapshots of him on his travels; and photographs of his "father, Pepino, and girlfriend" standing by Paris posters of Sanchez's 1953 exhibition at Bernheim-Jeune in Paris.
  Addition includes additional personal photographs of Sanchez; photographs of architecture, plant life, landscapes, street scenes, and cityscapes that Sanchez would use in his artwork; and photographs and slides of Sanchez's artwork including files on artwork sold tomuseums and individuals.
  Photographs are arranged by general subject category and then chronologically. Negatives can be found at the end of the series.
  - Family and Personal Photographs, 1922-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Family and Personal Photographs, 1964-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Portraits of Sanchez, 1965, 1967; Archival Resource Key; (contact sheets) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sources for Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Brazil, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Caribbean, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cuba, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mexico, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Miscellaneous and Unknown Locations, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Morocco, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - New England, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - New York, City, State, circa 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - New York, Long Island, E.F. Hutton House, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Pennsylvania, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Postcards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Puerto Rico, circa 1850s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-24)
    - Rhode Island, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Texas, Galveston, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Texas, Houston, Blaffer Hudson House, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - U.S. Virgin Islands, St. Croix, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - U.S. Virgin Islands, St. Thomas, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1946-1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34-37)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1958-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Negatives, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Family, Personal, and Sources for Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Morocco, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    - Photographs of Artwork, [1944], 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sanchez Working, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1949-1999, undated; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 26; (boxes 3-4; 17 folders)
  This series contains exhibition announcments, press releases, catalogs, publications, and news clippings containing information about Sanchez, and relating to one-man exhibitions of his artwork and group exhibitions in which he participated.
  - Announcements, Catalogs, and Reviews, 1950-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13-19)
  - Announcements, Catalogs, and Reviews, 1975-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Clippings, 1950s-1970s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5-10)
- Calendars, 1967-1976; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 4-5; 7 folders)
  This series contains eight day-book calendars with notations about appointments. There are no calendars for 1970 and 1971.
  - Calendars, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Calendars, 1969-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
- Sketches, circa 1940-1990, undated; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 4.6 Linear feet Boxes 5-24, 26-27, 32, 33-36; (boxes 5-6, sols 7-11, OV's 12-22, RD 23-24; 2.9 linear ft.)
  This series contains hundreds of original sketches by Sanchez, both loose and in sketchbooks. The sketches are primarily in pencil, but some are in ink and some are colored and include layouts for posters, and several proofs for lithographs. In addition to basic sketches capturing Sanchez's impressions drawn in a variety of locations throughout the world, the development of Sanchez's work on certain subjects is documented more fully in large groups of sketches, such as those of Boston City Hall and of his illustrations for the book Arte del Peru Colonial.
  The majority of the sketches are of buildings and of architectural and interior features of buildings, particularly windows and doorways. Additional subjects include landscapes, seascapes, cityscapes, flowers and plants, sunsets, and figure drawings. Many of the sketches have notations by Sanchez indicating the location in which they were made or the project they were associated with, and some are dated. Notations may also indicate the medium of artwork, or the name of the individual work, that a sketch was used for.
  Additional material consists of sketchbooks and sketches primarily of faces, dolls and figurines, shoes, and various types of fashion.
  The series is organized into three subseries:
  6.1: Sketchbooks, 1948-1976, undated
  6.2: Loose Sketches, circa 1940-1979, undated
  6.3: Oversized Loose Sketches, 1945-1979, undated
  Wherever possible, sketches are arranged alphabetically according to locations or subjects identified by Sanchez, and then chronologically. Undated sketches have been placed at the beginning of the appropriate subject category; unidentified sketches are at the end of the appropriate subseries. Occasionaly, subjects or locations may overlap, for example: sketches of doorways will be filed by location if one is noted on the sketch, but will otherwise be filed under "Unidentified Doorways."
  - Sketchbooks, 1948-1976, undated; 6.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Becqui Island, Bus Terminal in New York, Sunsets in New York, 1975, undated; Archival Resource Key; (3 books) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Brazil, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - England, 1948; Archival Resource Key; (2 books) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Europe, 1948; Archival Resource Key; (4 books) (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Morocco, 1972; Archival Resource Key; (2 books) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Morocco, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - New York, Studio, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Puerto Rico, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key; (6 books) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Puerto Rico, Saba, St. Maarten, St. Thomas, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key; (2 books) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Puerto Rico, San Juan, 1976, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 books) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sunsets in New York, 1975; Archival Resource Key; (2 books) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Sunsets in New York and Virgin Gorda, Ships, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Vermont, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified Sketchbooks, undated; Archival Resource Key; (4 books) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1940-1979, undated; 6.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Barbados, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Boats, Ships, 1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bogota, 1969, 1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Capri, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Cartagena, 1970-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Connecticut, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Cuba, 1946-1959, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Cuba, Near Havana, 1948-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Cuba, Teatro Marti, Havana, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Delaware, 1946, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - England, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Flowers and Plants, 1956-1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - France, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Grenada, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Haiti, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Human Figure, 1949, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Illustrations for Arte del Peru Colonial, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3-8)
    - La Rochelle, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Maine, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Massacusetts, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Morocco, 1972, 1978, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - New Hampshire, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - New Orleans, 1965, 1970, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - New York, Brooklyn, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - New York City, State, 1945-1950, 1978, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - [New York], Fisher's Island, 1963, 1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - New York, Glen Falls, John Rugge House, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - New York, Long Island, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - New York, Studio, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
    - New York, Sunsets, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - New York, World Trade Center, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Pennsylvania, 1950, 1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Pennsylvania, Schoolhouse Country Home Near Wanamaker, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Puerto Rico, 1963-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
    - Rhode Island, Tiverton Flower Sketches, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Rio De Janeiro, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - St. Barthélemy (St. Barts), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - St. Maarten, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - San Andres, 1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - San Luis, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - South Carolina, Charleston, 1946, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Spain, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Sunsets, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Tapestry Designs, 1944, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Texas, 1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Texas, Ranch Near Austin, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Virgin Islands, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Vermont, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Washington, D.C., undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Architecture, 1940s-1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3-10)
    - Unidentified Doorways, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Interiors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified Landscapes and Seascapes, 1955-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
    - Unidentified, Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Loose Sketches, 1945-1979, undated; 6.3; Archival Resource Key
    Some of the categories found in this subseries repeat, and overlap with, those found in 6.4 but the sketches are larger and are therefore stored in oversized folders. The final entry in the subseries is out of sequence but has been separated because it represents several sketches of architecture that were too large to store in oversized folders.
    - Boston City Hall Project, Working Sketches, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 12)
    - Boston City Hall Project, Working Sketches, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 13)
    - Boston City Hall Project, Working Sketches, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 14)
    - Christmas Card Ideas, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 15)
    - Circus, 1969-1970, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 15)
    - Cuba, 1950, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 15)
    - "El Zaguan,", 1968-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 16)
    - Fabric Design, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 16)
    - Horizons, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 16)
    - Illustrations for Arte del Perú Colonial, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 16)
    - New England, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
    - New Orleans, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
    - New York City, 1945-1950; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
    - New York, Long Island, E. F. Hutton House, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
    - Phipps House, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
    - Poster Designs, 1965, 1968, 1978, undated, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
      (includes original working sketch and finished poster for 1978 Sanchez exhibition at Williams College Museum of Art; also #20 of 50 posters for 1968 Sanchez exhibition at Associated American Artists, signed)
    - Puerto Rico, 1964-1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - Puerto Rico Landscape Project, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - St. Maarten, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - Tapestry Designs, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - Texas, Galveston, 1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - Trinidad, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
    - Unidentified Architecture, 1950-1977, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 19)
    - Unidentified Architecture, 1950-1977, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
    - Unidentified Architecture, 1950-1977, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 21)
    - Unidentified Doorways, 1965-1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
    - Unidentified, Miscellaneous, 1972, 1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
    - Architecture, Various, circa 1960s-1970s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Roll 23, Roll 24)
- Unprocessed Addition to the Emilio Sanchez Papers, 1949-2012; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 10.1 Linear feet boxes 25-34, OV 35
  Scope and Contents
  The unprocessed addition is 10.1 linear feet and contains biographical materials, correspondence, writings, photographs, works of art, subject files, printed materials, and scrapbooks. Biographical materials include address books, birth certificates, naturalization documents, and family-related documents. Correspondence is personal and professional and is with family, friends and museums. Writings are personal and include a log book and a typed transcription (possibly incomplete). Photographs are of Sanchez, his family, works of art, and source subjects for works of art, as well as CD-Roms of works of art. Some photographs assembled by Hugh Harrison, long-time friend of the Sanchez. Works of art include 10 sketchbooks and loose sketches. Also included are a drawing and 4 prints by Estrella Fonts, Sanchez's mother. Subject files include a print register, appraisals, mailing lists, and consignments. Printed material includes exhibition announcements and clippings. Also included are 3 scrapbooks, 2000-2012, that chronicle the history of the Emilio Sanchez Foundation's activities, including press releases, photographs, and exhibition-related material and hard drives of the foundation's databases in Filemaker format.
  - Unprocessed Papers, 1949-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 25)